Finding Aid for Rollo G. Conlin Papers 1948-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rollo G. Conlin Papers 1948-1966
Conlin, Rollo G., 1903-1974.
5 linear feet
Republican state representative from Tipton, Michigan, 1945-1967; member of the House Ways and Means Committee; chairman of the Committee on General Taxation; the State Tax Study Commission, 1957-1959; and the Joint House and Senate Committee on Constitutional Implementation. Correspondence, reports, subject files, sound recordings, and other papers largely relating to problems of state taxation in the administrations of G. Mennen Williams and John B. Swainson.
85994 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 1973 by Mrs. Rollo Conlin and her daughter Jeane A. Johnson (donor no. 5433 )
The collection is open for research.
Rollo Conlin, born on a farm in Tipton, Michigan (Lenawee County) to Thomas and Nettie (Camburn) Conlin, was educated in the Tipton public schools and Cleary Business College (Ypsilanti). From 1922 to 1928, he was employed as a toolmaker in Detroit and, in 1928, he married Pauline Snoddy of Milan, Michigan. Conlin returned to his home town to manage the family farm, eventually becoming involved in local politics. For eight years he represented Franklin Township on the Lenawee Board of Supervisors, was a member of the Tipton School Board for five years, and a director of the United Savings Bank of Tecumseh.
Running as a Republican in 1944, Conlin won a seat in the Michigan House of Representatives, a position he held continuously until 1966 when he met defeat in the Republican primary. As a member of the House, his chief interest was in fiscal matters, especially taxes. In 1954, he authored the so-called "Conlin Plan" which revised the Sales Tax Diversion clause in the Constitution as it related to school allocation. He was also the author of legislation establishing diagnostic centers for mental health treatment. In the late 1950's, Conlin was chairman of the Michigan Tax Study, a joint legislative and citizen committee. He also chaired the Joint House and Senate Committee on Constitutional Implementation concerned with governmental reorganization. He was also a member of House committees on economic development, general taxation, liquor control and the Michigan Commission on Interstate Cooperation.
The collections has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Speeches and press releases; Taxation Legislation and related background information; Other Legislative Matters; Committee on Statutory Implementation of the Constitution; Visual Materials; and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Conlin, Rollo G., 1903-1974.; Legislators--Michigan.; Lenawee County (Mich.); Michigan. Constitution, 1963.; Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan. Legislature. Special Legislative Committee on Taxation.; Republican Party (Mich.); Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.; Taxation--Michigan.; Tipton (Mich.); Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Conlin, Rollo G., 1903-1974.
Subjects - Sound Recordings
Bagwell, Paul D.; Conlin, Rollo G., 1903-1974.; Elections--Michigan--1960.; Michigan. Legislature. House of Representatives.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Swainson, John B. (John Burley), 1925-1994.; Taxation--Michigan.; Taxation--Law and legislation--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence
  - 1948-1954 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1955 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1955 (Box 1)
  - 1956 (Box 1)
  - June-July 1957 (Box 1)
  - August-October 1957 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1958 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1958 (Box 1)
  - January-April 1959 (Box 1)
  - May-December 1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - January-April 1964 (Box 1)
  - May 1964, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - June-August 1964 (Box 1)
  - September-December 1964 (Box 1)
  - August 1966 (Box 1)
- Speeches and Press Releases
  - 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958 (Box 1)
  - 1959-1962 (Box 1)
  - Undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Taxation Legislation and related background information
  - Joint Legislative Interim Committee Studying Tax and, Revenue Laws in Michigan 1951 (Box 1)
  - "The Support of State Services in Michigan," a report to the Joint Legislative Interim Committee Studying Tax and Revenue Laws in Michigan 1952 (Box 1)
  - "Conlin Plan" revising the Sales Tax Diversion Clause of the Michigan Constitution 1954 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Tax Study
    - Minutes September 4, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Minutes January 7, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Minutes May 6, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Tax Study Subcommittee minutes March 28, 1958 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Tax Study Memoranda 1958 (Box 2)
    - Legislation and the Michigan Tax Study 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Summary of Research Staff Reports of the Michigan Tax Study compiled by Citizens Research Council of Michigan (1958) (Box 2)
    - Michigan Tax Study Research Report, "Who Pays the Michigan Taxes?" by Richard A. Musgrave and Darwin W. Daicoff, Department of Economics, University of Michigan 1958 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Tax Study Staff Report, "The Corporate Income Tax" by Milton C. Taylor, Department of Economics, Michigan State University 1958 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Tax Study Miscellaneous papers 1958 (Box 2)
  - Taxation conferences 1956, 1960, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Public hearings of the General Taxation committee 1955 (Box 2)
  - General fund revenues, papers regarding 1952 (Box 2)
  - General Taxation Committee Minutes and Reports 1959 (Box 2)
  - Taxes on business receipts and corporate profits 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  - Taxes on corporate profits 1955 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Income Tax 1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - General fund revenues 1952 (Box 2)
  - General fund revenues 1956-1958 (Box 2)
  - Gift and estate taxes 1957 (Box 2)
  - Intangible tax 1958 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous assessments of state bills related to taxation, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous opinions on taxation, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Other Legislative Matters
  - State support of higher education 1953 (Box 3)
  - Michigan politics especially regarding the State Legislature 1953-1957 (Box 3)
  - State aid to public schools 1955-1956, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Public hearings regarding airlines 1955-1958 (Box 3)
  - Wayne State Study Commission 1955 (Box 3)
  - Taxation of mines in Michigan 1955-1957, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Secretary of State branches and political patronage 1956 (Box 3)
  - Diagnostic centers for mental health treatment 1956 (Box 3)
  - Taxation of agricultural products 1956 (Box 3)
  - Forestry 1957, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Sales taxes on alcoholic beverages 1958 (Box 3)
  - Legislative agents registered in 1960 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Committee on Statutory Implementation of the Constitution
  - Working files on constitutional implementation 1963, 4 volumes (Box 4)
  - Opinions of Attorney General's Office on Constitutional Implementation 1963 (Box 4)
- Visual Materials
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Film; Interview relating to implementation of new Michigan constitution, circa 1964, 16 mm., b&w, sound, ca. 20 min. (Box 5)
- Sound Recordings
  - Testimony of Al Perline, tax counsel, J. L. Hudson Co. on SB1125 and SB1396 undated, 1 reels; 3 3/4 ips; 5 in. (Box 5)
  - Discussion on taxes with state treasurer Sanford Brown, House speaker Don Pears, and Rollo G. Conlin undated WJR Detroit, 1 reels; 3 3/4 ips; 5 in. (Box 5)
  - Hearings on House Resolution 128, held at Metropolitan Airport Detroit; and at Kent Co. Airport, Grand Rapids, Mich. undated, 1 reels; 7 1/2 ips and 3 3/4 ips; 7 in.; 2 sides (Box 5)
    changes from 7 1/2 ips to 3 3/3 ips early in the tape
  - Discussion re. Kalamazoo probate judges, and the Diagnosis Center circa 1956, 1 reels; 3 3/4 ips; 5 in. (Box 5)
  - Tax study committee hearings, Kellogg Center Lansing December 2, 1958, 2 reels; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 5)
  - Discussion re. November 1959 state tax problem. With Don Potter, WJIM, Lansing, 1959, 1 reels; 3 3/4 ips; 5 in. (Box 5)
  - WJR Sunday Supplement program (re. Michigan tax situation) June 14, 1959, 1 reels; 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Box 5)
  - WJR Sunday Supplement program (re. Michigan tax situation) November 1, 1959, 1 reels; 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Box 5)
  - Discussion in class of D. Cline and (?) Taylor at MSU 1960, 1 reels; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 5)
  - Debate between John B. Swainson and Paul Bagwell, candidates for governor October 1960, 1 reels; 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Box 5)
  - Public hearing on SB1396 and SB1145 April 25, 1961, 1 reels; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 5)
  - WJIM television program, "Channel 6 Reports" September 1961, 30 min; 1 reels; 7 1/2 ips; 7 in. (Box 5)
  - Government reorganization hearings 1963, 2 reels; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 5)
  - Political advertisement WABJ 1964 primary (includes Romney ad. and Conlin ads.), 1 reels; 7 1/2 ips; 5 in. (Box 5)
  - "Meet the Press" interview with George Romney November 13, 1966, 1 reels; 3 3/4 ips; 7 in. (Box 5)